It's a story of a couple
who wanted to have a child.
They wanted their child to be born deaf.
The reason is that both
of the partners were themselves deaf,
and they wanted a child like themselves.
So they sought out a sperm donor.
They needed a sperm donor in any case,
because this was a lesbian couple.
They sought out a sperm donor who was himself deaf
and who had five generations of deafness in his family.
They conceived a child, and they succeeded.
Their child was born deaf.
They were born deaf.
They had no other children.
They had no other child.
They had no other mother.
The case of a deaf couple
who wanted to have a deaf child
raises one of the hard questions of the boundaries.
They argued that deafness,
is not a disability, but it's a distinctive identity.
Now, is deafness a disability?
Were they impairing the child?
Or were they creating a
child with an identity like theirs?
That was a big debate.
It was a controversial case.
So we do, I think, have to
recognize that there will be borderline cases.
And we will have to
argue as a society and debate.
How to regard deafness.
Or a tendency to obesity.
Or baldness.
Or what about teeth, straightening of teeth in orthodontia.
Are these medically necessary?
Or are they purely preferential?
But what this means is that
the new era of genetic technology
requires that we have a public debate
about the meaning of health,
and I would say also the limits of genetic technology.
I think some of the
most penetrating, interesting criticisms and worries
about biotechnology and genetic engineering
have come to us in popular culture,
including novels and film.
Like most parents of their time,
they were determined that their next child
would come into the world in what had become
the natural way.
Their extracted ovules,
the marie,
have been fertilized with Antonio's sperm.
After the exploration, we have two healthy boys
and two very healthy girls.
Naturally, without any predisposition
to any hereditary disease.
All that remains is to select the most compatible candidate.
First, we can decide the sex.
Have you thought about it?
You see, we would like Vincent to
have a brother to play with him.
Of course. Hello, Vincent.
Hello.
I think there is a tendency today
to embrace genetic technology and bioengineering,
not only for health,
where I think it's entirely appropriate,
but also to give parents more choice
about the genetic characteristics of their children.
One of the most successful sperm banks in the world
is called California Cryobank.
It's a for-profit company. They sell sperm.
And they sell sperm which is carefully calculated,
cataloged according to the
genetic characteristics of the donors.
And very few donors are accepted.
How do they choose the sperm donors?
This company.
They advertise for donors in college newspapers.
The compensation, what do you suppose the compensation is?
It's up to $900 per month.
Ivy League sperm, they advertise.
Not only that, they provide detailed information
about the physical characteristics of each donor,
ethnic origin, college major.
Now, the company has no eugenic purpose.
They just want to make money.
It's a commercial company.
And I think that represents a danger.
And because what it does really is to turn children
and childbearing into an extension of the consumer society,
to turn children into commodities.
But in principle, what those technologies will make possible
will be an explosion of responsibility
of parents for the genetic design of their children.
Yeah, now get ready for the age of designer babies.
An L.A. fertility clinic says it will soon allow parents
to choose traits like gender, hair
color, eye color, and skin color.
Doctors there are using technology,
usually use the screen for diseases,
and there is not a single law on
the books in this country to stop them.
So, this is the first self-replicating
species that we've had on the planet
whose parent is a computer.
It also is the first species to have
its own website encoded in its genetic code.
So, in that case, it's possible that
children will come to hold their parents responsible
for their genetic characteristics, for
their height, for their physical appearance,
maybe even for their academic performance.
I think that would damage
the relation between parents and children,
and it would really be
also the commodification of the relationship
between parents and children.
And I think those consumer uses of genetic engineering
are morally impermissible.
But basically, there are two
agencies who can ultimately decide.
There is the market, which essentially
is what will make these decisions
if there is no public collective decision,
or there are democratic institutions.
And I hope that democratically
we will have a public debate
and a public decision taking about
the ethical limits of new biotechnology.